Okay, then it's time to talk about how
the United States got its big boy
industrial pants on during the Gilded
Age and all the massive changes that
came along with it. So, if you're ready
to get them brain cows milked, let's get
to it. Okay, so when we're talking about
industrialization during this period,
historians typically call it the Gilded
Age, which is a term that comes from our
boy Mark Twain. Now, if something is
gilded, that means it's covered in a
thin layer of gold. And so, for me, I
have always thought of the guilded age
as something like a gold covered turf. I
mean, yeah, it looks real fancy and
expensive, but under the gilding, it's
just a stanky turd. So in this video I
mostly want to talk about the gold and
then in the next video we're going to
talk more about the turd. So you know
get excited. Okay. So the guilded age
was a period that marked the rapid
expansion and influence of large-scale
industrial businesses and this
development led to profound economic
development and business consolidation.
Now to be clear the guilded age is not
the moment when America industrialized.
Now if you've been around for a while
you'll remember that large-scale
industrialization really began in the
first half of the 19th century with the
market revolution. But during this
second era of industrialization,
everything just got bigger and faster
and more profitable. And you're probably
asking, "But Heimler, what were the
factors contributing to that prodigious
growth?" You know, I got you, boo. And
so, there were four big causes of the
rapid expansion of industrialization
during this period. Now, the first two
causes I covered extensively in the last
video for 6.5. So, I'll just mention
them briefly here. The first cause was
technological change. And here we had
the expansion of railroads and
technologies like electricity that
enabled industrial production to soar.
And the second cause was the expansion
of communication networks especially the
telegraph which followed the railroads
and connected the vast reaches of the
country and then later internationally.
And then the third cause was the
simultaneous developments of
urbanization and territorial expansion.
You see industrial cities were growing
rapidly and creating all kinds of jobs
for immigrants and rural farmers who
were out of work thanks to the
increasing commercialization of
agriculture were going to take those
jobs. And because Americans were
expanding westward that provided both
new markets for goods and access to more
and more natural resources. But it is in
fact the fourth cause of
industrialization that I want to spend
some real time with because it's uh a
real important. But before I tell you
what it is, if your A push grade isn't
even a gilded turd but just a regular
old common rarity turd, then you might
want to check out my A push himler
review guide. It has everything you need
to get an A in your class and a five on
your exam in May and it's the fastest
way to study and that link is down in
the description. So you know have a
look. Okay, so the fourth cause of
America's rapid expansion of
industrialization is a series of pro
business government policies. Now the
common understanding of this period goes
something like this. The Gilded Age was
a period of unparalleled business
innovation and an accumulation of wealth
beyond belief. And that was all possible
because the government got out of the
way and let businessmen do their thing
without hindrance. And to be fair, there
is actually plenty of truth in that
statement. Like in general, the federal
government heavily supported the growth
of industry during this period by
adopting a lair attitude toward
regulation. It was an idea rooted in
Adam Smith's theory of free market
economics, which argued that the best
recipe for economic flourishing was to
allow businesses to compete amongst
themselves. The one thing that would
absolutely stifle such economic
flourishing, however, was any hint of
interference by the stupid government.
But flip that coin right over and you
get the reality that is almost never
mentioned, namely that a whole flurry of
laws were passed during this time which
facilitated the expansion and growth of
big business. For example, the McKinley
tariff of 1890 raised taxes on imported
goods to 50% which served the interests
of business owners since they could take
advantage of selling their products
cheaper than foreign imports. And a big
reason many politicians did not support
government regulation and business is
because they themselves had deep ties to
large corporations and profited
handsomely from their success. And we'll
talk about that in a later video.
Anyway, these kinds of reckless economic
practices hurt average consumers, none
more so than farmers who depended on
railroads to ship their goods to market.
And so far, the government refused to
regulate the railroad industry and
therefore rail companies charged
exorbitant prices for shipping
agricultural goods. But by 1887, farmers
had put enough pressure on Congress that
they passed the Interstate Commerce Act,
which created the Interstate Commerce
Commission. It was a government agency
responsible for regulating railroad
prices and ensuring fairness in pricing.
But over the next 20 years, the Supreme
Court heard 16 cases against railroad
corporations and they sided with the
corporations 15 times. So even when
regulation was imposed, it was quickly
defanged in favor of a more lzair
approach. And so that combined with
policies like government sponsored land
grants given to big railroad companies
really added up to one thing. Industrial
businesses grew rapidly both because the
government did not regulate them and
because the government helped that
growth by passing favorable policies.
And if that doesn't completely register,
think about it in simple terms like this
ball and plane. The ball represents
industrial businesses and most people
think it was able to roll along the
plane so well because the government
didn't throw any obstacles in its path.
And that's true. But what's equally true
is that the government actually inclined
the plane. and so that the ball would
roll faster. So the point is industrial
corporations owed much of their progress
to government help. Okay. Now that we
considered the environmental factors
that led to the explosion of
industrialization, let's consider four
developments that occurred within
businesses themselves that generated a
rise in productivity. So first we had
redesigned financial structures and the
big one to know here is the corporation.
Now corporations of course were not a
new thing during this period. No, all
those joint stock companies that we
talked about way back in unit 2 are like
the great granddaddies of the guilded
age corporation. But the difference is
that during the guilded age, the
corporation became the main way in which
large businesses were structured. Now,
essentially, a corporation is a business
structure that allows for investment
with the protections of limited
liability. In other words, an investor
can only lose the amount of money
invested and no more. But there was no
upper limit on the amount the investor
could earn if the company did well. And
so, since corporations were low-risk
investments with potentially large
payouts, investors raced to put their
money into the ever growing industrial
businesses of the age. And then the
second big development in businesses
that led to increased productivity was
the management revolution. So because
these large corporations were becoming
exceedingly complex, a new layer of
workers was needed between the top level
executives and the workers at the
bottom. And that led to the introduction
of middle managers. They were given
goals and tasks by the executives and
owners. And they were responsible for
managing the growing labor force in the
business in order to asssure that those
goals were met. And then other middle
managers were responsible for tasks like
accounting and purchasing and directing
information etc. and they became known
as white collar workers because they
wore you know shirts with white collars
and fancy suits unlike the working class
who became known as blueco collar
workers. Okay. The third big development
included all the advances made in
marketing and so with a surplus of goods
to be sold corporations pioneered the
advertising industry in order to
persuade people to purchase their
products. And one major development here
was the rise of the mail orderer catalog
that enabled Americans to purchase goods
by mail which was kind of like a proto
Amazon.com. Now the most widespread of
these cataloges came from Montgomery
Ward and Sears and Robot. What's more,
these companies shipped purchased goods
to rural areas for free via the
everexpanding network of railroads with
the help of the US Postal Service. And
then the fourth factor that led to
increased productivity was a growing
labor force. And here two factors
combined to generate an enormous influx
of laborers that fueled the second
industrial revolution in the United
States. First was a significant upsurge
in European and Asian immigrants that
arrived during the guilded age looking
for work. And we're going to get all
cozy with them in the next video. Second
was the deskkilling of labor that
occurred with the domination of
industrial factory work. You see,
factories had refined the process of
mass-producing goods with machines. And
that meant that the humans who worked in
factories needed no specialized skills
to perform their jobs. Like their
resumes only consisted of a pulse check,
and if the heart was beaten, then baby,
you're hired. Therefore, these large
corporations could essentially hire
anyone, regardless of skill, to work for
them. And this was a big part of the
change that came with the management
revolution that I mentioned earlier. It
meant that training people for jobs was
a whole lot easier because each person
was just specializing in a very specific
single task. But wait, there's more.
Industrial business leaders also got
real innovative in developing techniques
to increase their wealth by eliminating
their competition. And there are three
of these techniques you'll need to know.
And quick note, I'm going to give you a
name to associate with each practice.
But don't think that person was the only
industrialist who used such strategies.
No, they all kind of did all of them,
but some are more associated with
certain practices than others. Okay. The
first technique was called vertical
integration, which was a strategy by
which a corporation sought to control
every step in the process of the
production and sale of their goods. Now,
if you want a name to associate with
this, and I know you do, then meet
Andrew Carnegie, who was the founder of
the Carnegie Steel Company. Now, in case
you're not a steel producer yourself,
then let me tell you that the production
of steel required several steps, and
each step was carried out by a different
company. For example, one company was
responsible for mining the raw
materials, another for transporting
those raw materials to the factory,
another for processing raw materials
into steel, and yet another for shipping
the finished goods to market. And
because individual companies needed to
make profit on its own stage in the
process, that required higher prices for
the end product. So Carnegie went the
vertical integration route and
consolidated the entire process under
one corporation so that he controlled
the mining, the transportation and all
the rest. And in that way he was able to
cut cost significantly and increase his
own wealth rapidly. Okay. The second
method industrialists used to eliminate
competition was called horizontal
integration which was a process by which
a corporation concentrated wealth by
acquiring competing businesses. And the
name most associated with this method
was John D. Rockefeller who owned the
Standard Oil Company. Now, because of
the size of his corporation, he was able
to undercut the prices of his
competitors. And then when they couldn't
compete, Rockefeller bought their
company. And at one point, by using this
technique, Rockefeller owned about
fourfifths of America's entire oil
industry and didn't really have to worry
about market competition any longer. It
would kind of be like if Netflix decided
it wanted the one ring to rule them all
and then bought up Paramount and Peacock
and Disney Plus and all the rest. And at
that point, without any intervention
from the government, Netflix can charge
us whatever they want. And what are we
going to do? Not watch Stranger Things?
[laughter]
Don't be crazy. And then third,
industrialists eliminated competition by
creating trusts and holding companies.
Now, a trust is a monopoly in which
several businesses work together to
control a large portion of the market so
that they can charge whatever prices
they want since there no longer exists
any meaningful market competition to
check their predatory prices. And that's
what our boy Rockefeller did uh real
good. And then a holding company
describes the practice of buying
significant shares of stock in rival
companies with the intent to control
their decisions. And this was also a
Rockefeller special since he bought
significant amounts of shares in rival
oil companies and in that way he was
able to eliminate their market
competition in his industry. But the
point of all this is that a significant
amount of American wealth in the guilded
age became narrowly concentrated in the
hands of a few enormously wealthy
business tycoons. However, even though
that wealth gap was very much evident,
the process of industrialization during
this period raised the standards of
living for many Americans at the same
time. And we're going to pick up that in
a later video. Okay. And then the final
topic we need to consider here is the
push for big businesses to control new
international markets. You see, as the
world became increasingly
interconnected, business leaders sought
new relationships with foreign
countries, both for the markets they
provided and the raw materials within
their borders. And there were three
regions in particular that got them all
giddy. First, during the guilded age,
American industrialists began investing
heavily in the Pacific Rim territories,
most notably Hawaii. And the biggest
mover here was a California-based
corporation called Castle and Cook,
which established vast sugar plantations
there. And so that act by Castle and
Cook together with four other large
corporations meant that Hawaii became
increasingly dominated by an American
planter aristocracy that tied the
Hawaiian economy to the US economy. And
eventually these strong economic ties
would lead to a coup to overthrow the
indigenous queen Lily Ukalani in 1893
and ultimately to the US annexation of
Hawaii in 1898. And then second
industrialists turned their attention to
Asia and we'll concentrate here on
China. So historians typically refer to
China's experience in the 1800s by the
cheery title the century of humiliation
which is to say it was kind of a rough
hundred years over there. So European
industrial powers had forced China into
signing unequal treaties which resulted
in China being carved up into economic
spheres of influence in which each
western power had exclusive trading
rights. But since the US was kind of
late to the industrialization game,
American industrialists started to panic
on account of being excluded from access
to China's enormous market. So at the
end of this period, the US issued what
became known as the open door policy,
which wasn't legally binding, but still
guaranteed a US spot at the Chinese
economic table. And finally,
industrialists wanted to expand their
influence into Latin America. And a good
example here is the rise of the United
Fruit Company. Now, this was an American
company that took over several Latin
American territories and organized their
economies around the export of fruit,
most notably bananas. And that's why
these places became known as banana
republics. In Costa Rica, for example,
the United Fruit Company took over
800,000 acres, and the deal went like
this. We'll control this acorage for 99
years and in return we'll build
railroads and a shipping port to export
all these goods. But again, this
arrangement was all in favor of the
United States and not Costa Rica on
account of the intense economic control
the US was able to wield as a result of
this arrangement. Okay, you can click
here to watch my other unit 6 videos or
you can click here to grab my Himler
review guide which is going to help you
get an A in your class and a five on
your exam in May. I'm glad you stopped
by and I'll catch you on the flip-flop.
I'm lar.